<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook ID="ddi2-d1dae2a0-927b-013e-fb1c-02420a1c0304-nhis_00002.dat-nhis.ipums.org" version="2.5" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an Integrated Health Interview Series Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'nhis_00002.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-d1dae2a0-927b-013e-fb1c-02420a1c0304-nhis_00002.dat-nhis.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2026-02-23">February 23, 2026</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract nhis_00002.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2026-02-23">February 23, 2026</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="nhis">IPUMS NHIS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D071.V8.1</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2026-02-23"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Material Hardship Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">General Health Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Access to Care Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">General Coverage Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2447">
        <timePrd date="2024" event="single">2024</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  2024 NHIS
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="yes"><![CDATA[The Public Health Service Act (Section 308 (d)) provides that the data collected by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), may be used only for the purpose of health statistical reporting and analysis. Any effort to determine the identity of any reported case is prohibited by this law. NCHS does all it can to assure that the identity of data subjects cannot be disclosed. All direct identifiers, as well as any characteristics that might lead to identification, are omitted from the data files. Any intentional identification or disclosure of a person or establishment violates the assurances of confidentiality given to the providers of the information. 

Therefore, users will: 

Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only. 

Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director, NCHS, of any such discovery (301-458-4500). 

Not link these data files with individually identifiable data from other NCHS or non-NCHS data files. 

By using these data, you signify your agreement to comply with the above-stated statutorily-based requirements. ]]></confDec>
        <contact URI="http://www.nhis.ipums.org/" affiliation="IPUMS">Integrated Health Interview Series</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the NHIS database must cite it appropriately.  The citation is as follows:

Lynn A. Blewett, Julia A. Rivera Drew, Andrew Fenelon, Miriam L. King, Kari C.W. Williams, Daniel Backman, Etienne Breton, Grace Cooper, and Stephanie Richards. IPUMS Health Surveys: National Health Interview Survey, Version 8.1 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2025. https://doi.org/10.18128/D071.V8.1

If possible, citations should also include the URL for the NHIS site:  http://www.nhis.ipums.org.

Please see http://www.nhis.ipums.org/nhis/citation.shtml for precise formatting of the citation.]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[The Public Health Service Act (Section 308 (d)) provides that the data collected by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), may be used only for the purpose of health statistical reporting and analysis. Any effort to determine the identity of any reported case is prohibited by this law. NCHS does all it can to assure that the identity of data subjects cannot be disclosed. All direct identifiers, as well as any characteristics that might lead to identification, are omitted from the data files. Any intentional identification or disclosure of a person or establishment violates the assurances of confidentiality given to the providers of the information. 

Therefore, users must: 

Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only. 

Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director, NCHS, of any such discovery (301-458-4500). 

Not link these data files with individually identifiable data from other NCHS or non-NCHS data files. 

By using these data, you signify your agreement to comply with the above-stated statutorily-based requirements. 

Furthermore, users of NHIS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. Users must agree to the following conditions:
  
  
(1) Use the data in these data files for statistical reporting and analysis only 

(2) Make no use of the identity of any person or establishment discovered inadvertently and advise the Director of NCHS of any such discovery (301-458-4500) 

(3) Do not link these data with individually-identifiable data from NCHS or non-NCHS data files 

(4) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use and distribute these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute them to others. 

(5) Cite the NHIS appropriately.  Publications and research reports based on the database must cite it appropriately.  Please see http://www.nhis.ipums.org/nhis/citation.shtml

(6) NHIS cannot be used to study small geographic areas.  The smallest geographical areas identified in the NHIS are regions (groups of states) and a limited number of metropolitan areas.

(7) This system provides individual-level data only.  The NHIS Data Extraction System will not produce tables. You will need to use a statistical software package, such as Stata, SAS, or SPSS, to analyze the downloaded data.  Alternatively, you may use the NHIS-SDA tabulator to produce tables online, without making a data extract.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  Revision of (Analysis of health outcomes in rural/urban areas)]]></notes>
    <notes>This extract is a revision of the user's previous extract, ID 53936406.</notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>nhis_00002.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular"/>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr><var ID="YEAR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="YEAR">
  <location EndPos="4" StartPos="1" width="4"/>
  <labl>Survey year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[YEAR is a four-digit variable reporting the calendar year (e.g., 2003) the survey was conducted and the data were collected. YEAR indicates the survey year reported on the household record.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[This is a 4-digit numeric variable with 0 implied decimal places]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SERIAL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SERIAL">
  <location EndPos="10" StartPos="5" width="6"/>
  <labl>Sequential Serial Number, Household Record</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey year. The combination of YEAR and SERIAL provides a unique identifier for every household in the IPUMS NHIS database.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSERIAL is a 6-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="STRATA" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="STRATA">
  <location EndPos="14" StartPos="11" width="4"/>
  <labl>Stratum for variance estimation</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[STRATA is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable based on the NHIS sample design variables in the public use files concatenated with a sample design period indicator. STRATA represents the impact of the sample design stratification on the estimates of variance and standard errors. It is constant within a sample design period and changes between sample design periods. For analysis, researchers need to use STRATA in conjunction with PSU to account for stratification and clustering when computing variance estimates with IPUMS NHIS data.

See the User Notes on variance estimation for additional information.     

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSTRATA is a 5-digit numeric variable.

000:	Not in Universe]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PSU" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PSU">
  <location EndPos="17" StartPos="15" width="3"/>
  <labl>Primary sampling unit (PSU) for variance estimation</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PSU is the primary sampling unit variable that represents the impact of the sample design clustering on the estimates of variance and standard errors. It is constant within a sample design period and changes between sample design periods. For analysis, researchers need to use PSU in conjunction with STRATA to account for stratification and clustering when computing variance estimates with IPUMS NHIS data.  

See the User Notes on variance estimation for additional information.

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPSU is a 3-digit numeric variable.

000:	Not in Universe]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="NHISHID" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="NHISHID">
  <location EndPos="31" StartPos="18" width="14"/>
  <labl>NHIS Unique identifier, household</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[NHISHID is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey year. Using NHISHID, analysts can link IPUMS NHIS data with additional household-level data elements, from the NHIS source public use data files, that are not currently available in IPUMS.  NHISHID is a single variable constructed by concatenating multiple data elements from the NHIS source data files.  Analysts wishing to link person-level NHIS data should use the person-level linking key NHISPID.

See the user note on LINKING for instructions on how to create links between IPUMS NHIS and NHIS source data.  

After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesNHISHID is a 14-character string variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="URBRRL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="URBRRL">
  <location EndPos="32" StartPos="32" width="1"/>
  <labl>Urban-Rural county classification</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, URBRRL reports whether the household lives in a large central metro county, large fringe metro county, medium and small metro county, or nonmetropolitan county.

County Classification Scheme&nbsp;Counties are assigned to one of six levels according to the NCHS Classification Scheme, which are further collapsed to four levels in the NHIS public use files. The classification scheme "was developed for use in studying associations between urbanization level of residence and health and for monitoring the health of urban and rural residents." This classification scheme is periodically updated; please see the comparability tab for more information.

Counties designated as "Large central metro" are counties in MSAs (metropolitan statistical areas) with a population of 1 million or more that contain the entire population of the largest principal city, have their entire population in the largest principal city, or contain at least 250,000 inhabitants of any principal city of the MSA. "Large fringe metro" are counties in MSAs with a population of 1 million or more that do not qualify as large central metro counties. "Medium and small metro" are counties in MSAs with a population of less than 1 million. "Nonmetropolitan" are counties that are not in an MSA.After the 2019 redesign, there is no longer a sampling weight to produce household population estimates. See the user note on the calculation and use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Large central metro</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Large fringe metro</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Medium and small metro</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Nonmetropolitan</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PERNUM" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PERNUM">
  <location EndPos="34" StartPos="33" width="2"/>
  <labl>Person number within family/household (from reformatting)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable that numbers all persons within each family or within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they appear in the original NHIS data.  PERNUM was created by IPUMS NHIS during the process of reformatting the original NHIS public use files. 

Prior to 2019, PERNUM numbers all persons within each family. Beginning in 2019, PERNUM numbers all person within a household and has a maximum of "2," as only the sample child and sample adult are identified in the original NHIS data. For more information, see the Comparability section.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="NHISPID" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="NHISPID">
  <location EndPos="50" StartPos="35" width="16"/>
  <labl>NHIS Unique Identifier, person</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[NHISPID is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed value that is an identifying number unique to each person in a given survey year.  Using NHISPID, analysts can link IPUMS NHIS data with additional data elements, from the NHIS source public use data files, that are not currently available in IPUMS.  For example, researchers can use NHISPID to link variables in IPUMS NHIS with other variables from the core NHIS files variables.  Alternatively, users may use NHISPID to link variables from IPUMS with variables from NHIS supplements that are not yet part of IPUMS NHIS. NHISPID is a single variable constructed by concatenating multiple data elements from the NHIS source data files.  

Analysts wishing to link household-level NHIS data should use the household-level linking key NHISHID.

See the user note on LINKING for instructions on how to create links between IPUMS NHIS and NHIS source data.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesNHISPID is a 16-character string variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="HHX" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="HHX">
  <location EndPos="57" StartPos="51" width="7"/>
  <labl>Household number (from NHIS)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, HHX reports the person's household number on the original NHIS data. HHX is unique within sample but only unique across samples when combined with information on year. Prior to 2019, this variable was available for all persons.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[This is a 7-digit numeric variable with 0 implied decimal places]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="character"/>
</var>
<var ID="SAMPWEIGHT" dcml="3" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SAMPWEIGHT">
  <location EndPos="69" StartPos="58" width="12"/>
  <labl>Sample Person Weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SAMPWEIGHT is an IPUMS NHIS-constructed variable that represents, with a few exceptions, the random selection of a sample person in the household to complete a supplement survey.  (The exceptions to this generalization are the 1983 health insurance supplement and 1993 health insurance, access to care, and family resources supplements, which were asked of all persons in the second half of the year.)

For survey years 1997 forward, SAMPWEIGHT is based on the Final Annual Sample Adult and Sample Child Weights in the original NHIS public use files. This weight should be used with variables taken from the sample adult or sample child supplements for 1997 on (as indicated by the supplement title in the "Source" section toward the top of each variable description). 

SAMPWEIGHT also contains the sampling weights for a subset of the pre-1997 supplements, for which the definition of a sample person, and the rules governing the selection of sample persons, are less consistent. The universe statements for SAMPWEIGHT document who was included in the supplements requiring use of this weight on a year-by-year basis. SAMPWEIGHT consistently represents the inverse probability of selection into a supplement, adjusted for non-response with additional post-stratification adjustments for age, race/ethnicity, and sex using the Census Bureau's population control totals.

Users should review the documentation for extracted variables--most notably the "Weights" section toward the top of each variable description--to ascertain which weight is the appropriate choice for a given survey year. See the User Notes on the use of sampling weights for additional information.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSAMPWEIGHT is a 12-digit numeric variable with three implied decimals. That is, values of 012345678912 should be interpreted as 12345678.912. The command files delivered with IPUMS extracts automatically divide SAMPWEIGHT by 1,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="ASTATFLG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="ASTATFLG">
  <location EndPos="70" StartPos="70" width="1"/>
  <labl>Sample adult flag</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[ASTATFLG identifies the record of a sample adult. A sample adult is the one person over age 18 per household who is randomly selected to complete the sample adult questionnaire. For 1997-2018, a sample adult is the one adult per family who was selected at random by the computerized survey instrument to answer additional health-related questions, under the survey design instituted in 1997.  All persons other than sample adults (those not having the value 1 in ASTATFLG) are coded as "not in universe" for variables derived from the additional questions asked only of sample adults.  (Some additional questions were asked of both sample adults and sample children.)  Every adult in each family, except for active duty armed forces members, was eligible to be selected as the sample adult.  

Prior to 2019, ASTATFLG has the value "no one selected as sample adult" (code 4) for all adults in the family in the following two cases: 1) sample adult status was incorrectly assigned to someone in the armed forces, or 2) it could not be ascertained which adult in the family was chosen as sample adult.   

For 2020 only, SALNGPRTFLG further distinguishes between sample adults included in the longitudinal sample and sample adults included in the partial sample. Please see the user note on COVID-related changes to the NHIS for more information on the longitudinal and partial samples.

A similar flag variable, CSTATFLG, identifies the record of a sample child.

This variable is automatically included in all extracts, but only has valid values for 1997 forward.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Sample adult, has record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Sample adult, no record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Not selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>No one selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Armed forces member</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>6</catValu>
    <labl>AF member, selected as sample adult</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CSTATFLG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="CSTATFLG">
  <location EndPos="71" StartPos="71" width="1"/>
  <labl>Sample child flag</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[CSTATFLG identifies the record of a sample child. A sample child is the one person under age 18 per household who is randomly selected to complete the sample child questionnaire. For 1997-2018, the sample child is the one person under age 18 per family who was selected at random by the computerized survey instrument for additional health-related questions, under the survey design instituted in 1997. All persons other than sample children (those not having the value 1 in CSTATFLG) are coded as "not in universe" for variables derived from these additional questions asked only of sample children.  (Some additional questions were asked of both sample adults and sample children.)   

Prior to 2019, Every child in each family, except for active duty armed forces members and emancipated minors, was eligible to be selected as the sample child.  Emancipated minors are persons age 14 to 17 who are married or living with a partner OR who live on their own without the supervision of a parent, other adult family member, or legal guardian.  

CSTATFLG has the value "no one selected as sample child" (code 4) for all children in the family in the following two cases prior to 2019: 1) if sample child status was incorrectly assigned to someone who was ineligible, or 2) if it was unknown which child in the family was chosen as sample child.   

A similar flag variable, ASTATFLG, identifies the record of a sample adult.

This variable is automatically included in all extracts, but only has valid values for 1997 forward.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Sample child-has record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Sample child-no record</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Not selected as sample child</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>No one selected as sample child</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Emancipated minor</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Person Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="POVLEV" dcml="2" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="POVLEV">
  <location EndPos="75" StartPos="72" width="4"/>
  <labl>Family income as a percentage of the poverty line, continuous</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, POVLEV reports the ratio of family income to the federal poverty line.

The ratio of family income to the federal poverty line is determined by dividing total family income (FAMTOTINC) by the appropriate poverty threshold relative to the family's size from the U.S. Census Bureau. For more information on how total family income is collected, please see FAMTOTINC, and for more information on the Census Bureau's official poverty thresholds, please see POORYN.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[POVLEV is 4 columns wide with 2 implied decimals.

10.00: Top code for ratio of family income to federal poverty line of 10 or more]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Material Hardship Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HEALTH" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HEALTH">
  <location EndPos="76" StartPos="76" width="1"/>
  <labl>Health status</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, HEALTH rates an individual's general health (as self-reported by the person in question or evaluated by a family member) on a four-point (1972-81) or five-point (1982 forward) Likert scale, ranging from "excellent" to "poor" (along with an unrated "unknown" category).

For 1997-2018, HSTATYR reports whether the health status of sample adults and sample children was better, worse, or about the same as one year ago.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Excellent</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Very Good</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Good</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Fair</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Poor</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">General Health Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="USUALPL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="USUALPL">
  <location EndPos="77" StartPos="77" width="1"/>
  <labl>Has usual place for medical care</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, USUALPL indicates whether individuals have a place (or more than one place) that they usually go when they are sick or need advice about their health. Please see the Universe tab for changes to the universe prior to 1997.

Text from the Field Representative's Manual for 1997 (which was not routinely read to respondents) clarified this inquiry by noting, "This is not necessarily the doctor most recently contacted. (For example, the most recent contact may have been with a specialist never seen before.) Additionally, it need not be a doctor or clinic the Sample Adult has ever contacted. In this case, the question refers to the doctor or place the Sample Adult would contact if he/she is sick or needs advice about his/her own health."]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>There is no place or No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, has a usual place or Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>There is more than one place</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Access to Care Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="TYPPLSICK" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="TYPPLSICK">
  <location EndPos="80" StartPos="78" width="3"/>
  <labl>Kind of usual place for medical care</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children who reported one or more usual places to go for care, or who answered "don't know" or "refused" in response to USUALPL, TYPPLSICK reports the type of place respondents usually go to when they are sick or need advice about their health. Please see the Universe tab for changes in the universe prior to 2019.

Beginning in 2019, if the sample adult or sample child had one or more usual place of care, did not know, or refused (USUALPL), interviewers asked, "What kind of place is it/do you go to most often-- a doctor's office or health center; an urgent care center, a clinic in a drug store or grocery store; a hospital emergency room; a VA Medical Center or VA outpatient clinic; or some other place?" Prior to 2019, if there was a "yes" response to the question about whether there is a place that the person usually goes when sick, interviewers asked, "What kind of place is it--a clinic, doctor's office, emergency room, or some other place?" If the response to the question was "there is more than one place," interviewers asked, "What kind of place do you go to most often--a clinic, doctor's office, emergency room, or some other place?"

Definitions&nbsp;The Field Representative's Manual for 1997-2000 states, "A place to USUALLY go when sick or in need of advice about one's health includes: Walk-in clinic, Doctor's office, Clinic, Health Center, Health Maintenance Organization, Hospital - Emergency room or outpatient clinic, Military or VA health care facility." The survey form recognized a smaller number of options: "Clinic or health center"; "Doctor's office or HMO"; "Hospital Emergency Room"; "Hospital outpatient department"; and "Some other place."

The Manual for 1995-2000 provided directions on distinguishing between a doctor's office and a clinic or health center. If the respondent used the term "clinic" or "health center," the interviewer was to record this. However, if the respondent was unable to classify the place as a doctor's office, clinic or health center, the interviewer was instructed to probe to determine how many doctors work out of the "place." A "place" with 3 or less doctors was to be considered a doctor's office.

Beginning in 2019, the Field Representative's Manual offers new definitions for interviewers inquiring about usual place of care. The Manual defines an urgent care center or clinic in a drug store or grocery store as "places where you do not need to make an appointment ahead of time, and do not usually see the same health care provider at each visit." The same document defines a doctor's office or health center as "a place where you see the same doctor or the same group of doctors every visit, where you usually need to make an appointment ahead of time, and where your medical records are on file."Related Variables&nbsp;In some years, interviewers also asked whether persons usually go to the same place identified in TYPPLSICK for their routine or preventive care (ROUTCARE) and, if not, the type of place where the person normally receives routine preventive care (PLACECAR). Other questions covered whether the person has changed the usual place of health care in the past twelve months, (if so) whether this change was for reason related to health insurance, and (in 1999) how long subject had been going to their usual source of health care and why some persons lacked a usual source of care.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>000</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>100</catValu>
    <labl>Doctor's office, clinic, or health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>110</catValu>
    <labl>Clinic or health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>111</catValu>
    <labl>Health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>112</catValu>
    <labl>Public health clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>113</catValu>
    <labl>Clinic, unspecified type</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>114</catValu>
    <labl>Community/immigrant/rural clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>115</catValu>
    <labl>Company or school clinic/center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>116</catValu>
    <labl>Urgent care/walk-in clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>117</catValu>
    <labl>Migrant clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>118</catValu>
    <labl>Rural health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>119</catValu>
    <labl>Community or family health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>120</catValu>
    <labl>Doctor's office or HMO</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>121</catValu>
    <labl>Doctor's office</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>122</catValu>
    <labl>HMO</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>123</catValu>
    <labl>Doctor's clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>124</catValu>
    <labl>Private doctor's office in hospital</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>130</catValu>
    <labl>Doctor's office or health center</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>200</catValu>
    <labl>Hospital emergency room</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>300</catValu>
    <labl>Hospital outpatient department</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>310</catValu>
    <labl>County/city/public/county hospital outpatient</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>320</catValu>
    <labl>Private/other hospital outpatient clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>400</catValu>
    <labl>Some other place</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>410</catValu>
    <labl>Psychiatric hospital/clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>420</catValu>
    <labl>VA hospital/clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>430</catValu>
    <labl>Military health care facility</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>440</catValu>
    <labl>Military or VA health care facility</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>450</catValu>
    <labl>VA Medical Center or VA outpatient clinic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>460</catValu>
    <labl>At home</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>470</catValu>
    <labl>Non-hospital place</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>480</catValu>
    <labl>Other places (1985: Includes known HMOs)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>500</catValu>
    <labl>Doesn't go to one place most often</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>997</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>998</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>999</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Access to Care Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="DELAYCOST" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="DELAYCOST">
  <location EndPos="81" StartPos="81" width="1"/>
  <labl>Medical care delayed due to cost, past 12 months</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[For sample adults and sample children, DELAYCOST indicates whether, during the past twelve months, individuals delayed seeking medical care because of worry about the cost. In 1993, DELAYCOST was asked of all persons in quarters 3 and 4 and in 1994-2018 it was asked of all persons. For 1997-2018, respondents were explicitly told not to include dental care when answering this question. Beginning in 2019, respondents were not told to exclude dental care when answering this question, but they were also asked whether, during the past 12 months, they had delayed getting dental care due to the cost (DELAYDT). 

 The Field Representative's Manual for 1993 forward noted, "Delayed assumes that medical care has been or will eventually be received."  This definition of the term was not routinely shared with respondents.

Related Variables&nbsp;Several other variables available for 1997 forward address reasons other than "worry about the cost" that caused sample adults and sample children to delay getting medical care.  The non-financial reasons for delays in getting medical care identified in these variables are: "you couldn't get an appointment soon enough" (DELAYAPPT); "the clinic/doctor's office wasn't open when you could get there" (DELAYHRS); "you couldn't get through on the telephone" (DELAYPHONE); "you didn't have transportation" (DELAYTRANS); and "once you get there, you have to wait too long to see the doctor" (DELAYWAIT). 

Available for 1997 forward, YBARCARE, which identifies individuals who needed but did not get medical care because they could not afford it during the past 12 months, covers some of the same ground as DELAYCOST.  However, the wording of the question for YBARCARE implies that medical care was foregone for financial reasons, while the wording of the question for DELAYCOST refers to care delayed for financial reasons.  The difference in these two variables may, however, be less than is implied by this semantic distinction.  In the case of some acute illnesses (such as respiratory infections and "stomach flu"), medical care that was delayed was doubtless ultimately foregone in many cases.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>7</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>8</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-not ascertained</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown-don't know (1993-96: DK or refused)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Access to Care Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HINOTCOV" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HINOTCOV">
  <location EndPos="83" StartPos="82" width="2"/>
  <labl>Has no health insurance (excluding single service plans)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HINOTCOV is a recoded variable created by the IPUMS NHIS staff that indicates, for sample adults and sample children (and, prior to 2019, all persons), whether the individual had any general health insurance coverage.  For 1976-1996, IPUMS NHIS staff identified uninsured persons as  those without any private insurance, or without public health insurance coverage through Medicaid, Medicare, military health care. Persons covered only by the Indian Health Service (1993-1996) are coded as having no health insurance. For 1997 forward, uninsured persons were identified as those who answered "no" to the question, "{Are you/Is  anyone} covered by any kind of health  insurance or some other kind of health care plan?" See the survey questions section below for more details.  

For most years, HINOTCOV refers to a current lack of insurance coverage; for 1990 to 1996, the variable refers coverage status during the previous month. 

Methods of Determining Lack of Insurance

The process used to ascertain the lack of insurance coverage reported in HINOTCOV changed over time.  A brief description is provided below, while further information on the data collection process appears in the User Note on Changes in Insurance Data Collection.
&nbsp;For 1976 to 1999, lack of health insurance was ascertained indirectly.  In other words, having no coverage was inferred from responses to a series of questions on various forms of coverage.  Interviewers asked about coverage through Medicare, Medicaid or other public assistance programs, military health care, and private insurance.  Persons not covered by any of these types of insurance were coded as having no health insurance.

For 1980 to 1996, persons who received Aid to Families with Dependent Children (AFDC) or Supplemental Security Income (SSI) were assumed to have health insurance coverage, since they were eligible for health care coverage (i.e., Medicaid) through these programs.

For 2000 forward, HINOTCOV reflects a response of "no coverage of any kind" to a direct question about what type of insurance the person had.Survey questions]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>No, has coverage</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, has no coverage</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown/refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">General Coverage Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
</dataDscr>
</codeBook>
